<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe report of the militarie seruices done in the Low Countries, by the Erle of Leicester: written by one that serued in good place there in a letter to a friend of his</title>
            <author>Digges, Thomas, d. 1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7285.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110913</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846366</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846366</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150835</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73873)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150835)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 289:9 or 1983:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe report of the militarie seruices done in the Low Countries, by the Erle of Leicester: written by one that serued in good place there in a letter to a friend of his</title>
                  <author>Digges, Thomas, d. 1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Arnold Hatfield, for Gregorie Seton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: T.D., i.e. Thomas Digges. Another edition (STC 7285) is unsigned.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 289:9 identified as STC 7285.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Leicester, Robert Dudley, --  Earl of, 1532?-1588 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150835:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150835:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE REPORT OF THE MILITARIE SERVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces done in the LOW COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRIES, by the Erle of LEICE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER: written by one that ſerued in good place there in a letter to a friend of his.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by Arnold Hatfield, for <hi>Gregorie Seton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1587</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note_on_dating_system">
            <pb facs="tcp:150835:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Note that the account of the daies, monethes, yeeres, and miles, is to be made al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in this letter after the ſtile and meaſure of ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150835:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL MY ESPECIALL GOOD FRIENDE SIR <hi>I. A.</hi> KNIGHT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, to ſatiſfie your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten earneſt requeſtes, I haue taken time theſe holydaies to ſet you downe a briefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of the military ſeruices done in the lowe Countries, by the Earle of <hi>LEICES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER,</hi> and his armies, during the time of his abode and gouernment there: reckening from the <hi>22.</hi> day of Ianuary <hi>1585.</hi> on which day he was receiued Gouernour of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; till the <hi>23.</hi> of Nouember <hi>1586.</hi> when he embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at <hi>VLVSHING,</hi> in his returne for <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> I entermeddle not with the eſtate of Religion, iuſtice, or ciuill pollicie, becauſe your letters demaund it not, and I willingly deale not further in reportes, then is by ſome kinde of dutie required of me. You expect not I hope but the ſubſtance of things done with breuitie: the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunces, I know, and particularities, will require a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable volume. Of one thing I muſt entreate you to be eſpecially excuſed. I will not meddle with the particular ſeruices of priuate men: becauſe if I ſhould rehearſe them all, and ſpeake of them as indeede they haue deſerued, it were aboue my ſkill, and I ſhould be longer then my lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſuffreth. And if I ſhould touch ſome, and conceale others, the iuſt offence would hardly be endured. For
<pb facs="tcp:150835:3"/> truth of the things I write you of, this be aſſured: what I write as done of our partie, either I ſawe, and am wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it my ſelfe, or I haue it by the credible report of thoſe that were the doers. What I ſet downe of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies doings, I either take it from their owne intercepted letters, or I do it vpon the aduertiſements of our beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers: who in circumſtances may erre, but ſwarue not much from truth, I thinke, in any materiall point: howſoeuer it is, I truſt you will be perſwaded, that I willingly ſpeake no vntruth: And then as I conceiue of theſe things, if ſo it pleaſe you to accept of them, they haue béene done, as I take them, in maner as followeth.</p>
            <p>After long and humble ſuite of the Eſtates generall of the vnited Prouinces of the lowe Countries, it pleaſed the Quéenes Maieſtie our Soueraigne to graunt vnto them a large and bountifull aide of men &amp; money, in ſuch ſort, and vpon ſuch Articles and conditions, as in the treatie concluded betwéene them, bearing date the fourth day of September, in the yéere <hi>1585.</hi> it more at large ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péereth. To ſpeake of the magnanimitie, wiſedome, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſingular goodneſſe of hir Maieſtie in yéelding ſo great and chargeable a ſuccour: with conſideration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom, vpon how neceſſarie and moſt vrgent cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and for how gréeuouſlie oppreſſed a people and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, it was intended, were a matter beſide my purpoſe at this time, and aboue the reach of my pen and ſkill. The fact is, and will be approoued, and renowmed in the world, ſo long as the memorie of wiſe and good Princes, and of true princely actions ſhal endure. But in the Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atie named, there is one Article amongſt others, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is eſpecially required, That it might pleaſe her Maieſtie to ſende with her forces into thoſe partes, a perſonage of nobilitie, valure and wiſedome, of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Nobilitie, as well to gouerne her people, as alſo to direct and to deale otherwiſe, and to vſe ſuch further
<pb facs="tcp:150835:3"/> préeminence and authoritie, as is ſpecified in the Treatie. The man for this purpoſe moſt deſired of the Eſtates, and eſpecially choſen by her Maieſtie, was the Earle of <hi>Leyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> who being accordingly appointed for this ſeruice, after his commiſſion receiued, and view taken of ſuch as were then to go with him, leauing whatſoeuer the ſingular bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God moſt happily many waies, and the eſpeciall fauour of a mightie Prince had of long time yéelded him in his owne Countrie; tooke leaue at the Courte, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted towardes <hi>Harwich</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> there to embarque in the beginning of December following. There accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in this voyage, the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> the Lord <hi>Awde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> the Lord <hi>North,</hi> with diuers Knights, and manie Eſquiers and Gentlemen, to the number of ſixe or ſeauen hundred horſe, brauely and ſouldiour like appointed, all vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaries and of his owne friendes, followers, &amp; ſeruants. He departed from <hi>Harwich</hi> with the moſt part of his traine the ninth day of December, and on the tenth of the ſame arriued at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>luſhing</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> where, &amp; at <hi>Middleborough</hi> he was receiued with great concourſe and ioye, and after two daies ſtaie there by ſundrie iournies came to the <hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> Here after many daies treatie: vpon the <hi>22.</hi> daie of Ianuary <hi>1585.</hi> he receiued the gouernement of thoſe Countries, with tytle of <hi>Gouernour and Captaine Generall</hi> of <hi>Holland, Zealand,</hi> and of the vnited Prouinces, and of their aſſociates. The vnited Prouinces, and their aſſociates were then accounted the Duchie of <hi>Gelders,</hi> with the Countie of <hi>Zutphen, Holland, Zealand, Vtricht,</hi> and the countries adioining of <hi>Frizeland,</hi> betwéene the riuer of <hi>Emes</hi> and <hi>Lawers, Flaunders</hi> alſo and <hi>Brabant,</hi> for the townes of thoſe countries, that then helde with the other vnited Prouinces. And the eſtate of them all was then this. In <hi>Holland, Zealand,</hi> and <hi>Vtricht</hi> the enimie had cléerly nothing: in <hi>Frizeland</hi> alſo nothing, ſauing that the citie of <hi>Gron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningen</hi> and that part of the countrie called <hi>Omelandes</hi> were
<pb facs="tcp:150835:4"/> wholie his: in <hi>Gelderland</hi> and <hi>Zutphen</hi> he had a good part: in <hi>Brabant</hi> the Eſtates had but <hi>Bergen apzome, Saint Ghertru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denberg, Hueſden, Graue,</hi> and <hi>Wowe</hi> caſtle, with the Forte of <hi>Lillo:</hi> in <hi>Flaunders</hi> they had <hi>Sluice,</hi> and <hi>Oostend,</hi> and the fortes of <hi>Terneuſe,</hi> the <hi>Dole, Lyſkenſhooke,</hi> and <hi>Saint Antonies hooke:</hi> all the reſt were the enimies, togither with all the other of the ſeauentéene Prouinces, except the whole al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of the countrie of <hi>Oueriſſell,</hi> which in a kinde of newe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tralitie, ſéemed to fauor the Eſtates party, and rather to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to them: but indéed did greatly aide the enimie with victuales and prouiſions, and had manie ſecrete intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with him.</p>
            <p>Theſe Prouinces, their eſtate, and the people of them did the E. of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> at this his firſt arriuall, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the gouernment find in great confuſion: The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people without obedience, The ſoldier in miſerie and diſorder for want of pay, The Gouernors weary, &amp; tired, for lacke of good aſſiſtance, and due obedience, The Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces themſelues ſtaggering in their vnion, &amp; euery Towne next danger readie to ſéeke newe meanes for their ſafetie: ſuch was their feare of the enimie triumphant nowe with continuall victories, and eſpecially with the late recouerie of <hi>Anwarpe:</hi> ſo little was their hope of their owne abilitie to reſiſt, and ſo many were the enimies déepe and ſecret practiſes, euen in the verie bowels of them.</p>
            <p>The eſtate dulie conſidered, and ſuch remedies to euerie member aptly applied, as the preſent time would then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: the ciuill gouernment being firſt in ſome good ſort well ſetled, the Earle applied himſelfe foorthwith to the militarie ſeruice, the firſt occaſion being offered for the reliefe of <hi>Graue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Graue</hi> is a Towne in <hi>Brabant,</hi> belonging to Count <hi>Mourice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> ſeconde ſonne to <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> deceaſed. But it was then in the gouernment of Count <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Hohenloe</hi> or <hi>Hollocke</hi> a Germaine, who
<pb facs="tcp:150835:4"/> had long ſerued the Eſtates, and had placed gouernour in this Towne <hi>Mounſieur Hemart,</hi> a Baron of theſe lowe Countries with garriſon of about eight hundred Dutch and Netherlande ſouldiours. The Towne is not great, but fortified of late, and made verie ſtrong by the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> whoſe patrimonie it was. It is of ſome importaunce, becauſe ſtanding vpon the riuer of <hi>Maſe,</hi> it hindereth the frée paſſage of that part of the riuer néere it. Otherwiſe for trade, territorie, wealth, or any other commoditie, it is not to be much accounted of. <hi>Alexander Farneſe,</hi> Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> gouernour then for the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> in <hi>Brabant, Flaunders,</hi> and thoſe parts of the lowe Countries that acknowledge the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> had ſent the Count <hi>Charles Maunſfelt,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaguere this Towne, and to beſiege it ſomewhat a far off, which he accordingly did, by erecting rounde about it foure fortes, with fiftéene hundred ſouldiours in them, and hauing néere him within one engliſh mile all the ſpaniſh Regiments, to the number of fiue thouſand foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. He had now lien there from December till about the beginning of March: at which time the E. of <hi>Leyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> vnderſtanding the Towne was brought into diſtres for lacke of men, victuals, and other prouiſions, mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to relieue it, and for the readie anſwering of all inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent occaſions to be more néere it, departed from the <hi>Hage</hi> by <hi>Harlem,</hi> and <hi>Amstelredam,</hi> to <hi>Vtricht.</hi> From thence he preſently ſent his horſemen being in number about thirtéene or fourtéene hundred, to encampe at <hi>Nyekircke</hi> in the prouince of <hi>Vellowe</hi> in Gelderland: aſwell to vnburden the Townes of them, as alſo by their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng there to deteine the enimies forces of thoſe partes from <hi>Graue.</hi> He appointed to Count <hi>Hollock,</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn Norris</hi> Coronell generall of the Engliſh infantery, about two thouſand footemen, without horſemen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the place was not for them, with direction to vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="tcp:150835:5"/> and to ſupplie and furniſh <hi>Graue,</hi> with all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Theſe Gentlemen marching with their troupes, tooke firſt by aſſault a little fort of the enimies about foure miles from <hi>Graue,</hi> called the <hi>Mill</hi> forte, and then mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to fortifie themſelues as néere the Towne as they might, and from their fortification to take ſuch order as occaſion ſhould miniſter, for atchieuing their intent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to intrench vpon the banke of the <hi>Maſe</hi> on <hi>Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſide, about two engliſh miles from <hi>Graue,</hi> betwéene it and <hi>Battenbourge</hi> caſtle, and within halfe a mile or thereabouts of the enimies bridge, and fortes on that ſide. They began their worke with about thrée hundred ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, and ſome pyoners on Tueſday at night in Eaſter-wéeke the <hi>5.</hi> of Aprill, and in the morning had raiſed it a yarde high, when the enimie hauing had intelligence of their meaning, ſendeth to hinder the ſame thrée thouſand Spaniardes: who after two or thrée attempts put our men being but few from their worke, and cauſed them to retire. But other of our troups to the number of eight or nine hundred, preſently méeting them, our men made ſtande againe, gaue a freſh charge vpon the Spaniardes, draue them ouer the fortification, where they fought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, euen to their owne forte, ſlaying on the ground fiue hundred of them all Spaniards: amongſt whom ſeauen ſpeciall captaines, and two others of greater account, and wounded about two hundred which were caried to <hi>Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke,</hi> &amp; other places. They tooke alſo one péece of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ordinance, brought to beate our boates and fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Of our men ſixe or ſeauen ſcore were ſlaine, but not one man of name. Sir <hi>Iohn Norris</hi> was hurt in the breſt with a pike: ſir <hi>Iohn Boroughes</hi> had a finger ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off with a muſket ſhot. After this fight, the Count <hi>Hollocke</hi> battered and tooke <hi>Battenbourge</hi> caſtle, and the forte <hi>de Guanden,,</hi> and the ſtrong houſe of <hi>Empell,</hi> and then his victual being come he victualed <hi>Graue</hi> by water twiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:150835:5"/> went himſelfe into it, ſupplied the garriſon with newe men, and left it furniſhed with all prouiſions ſufficient by acknowledgement of <hi>Hemart</hi> the captaine himſelfe for nine monethes. And hauing done that he came for, in the verie viewe and face of the enimie, he diſſolued his campe, and came away with great honor.</p>
            <p>A liftle before this time fell out the ſurpryſe of <hi>Wearle</hi> a great Towne in <hi>Weſtfalia</hi> by coronell <hi>Skenck,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards a ſharpe fight by the ſame <hi>Skenck,</hi> with thrée or foure thouſande of that countrie, where he ſlewe and ouerthrewe aboue two thouſand with great valure, and brought away rich ſpoiles: but being in the dioceſſe of <hi>Colloigne,</hi> and without the iuriſdiction of the vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, and not directly againſt their chiefe enimie. I wil enlarge no further of theſe exploites.</p>
            <p>The prince of <hi>Parma</hi> (as it was reported to vs) was much kindled with this ouerthrow at <hi>Graue,</hi> with the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the caſtles and victualing of the Towne: and his former winter preparations being nowe in readines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beginning of Maie he began to march towardes <hi>Graue,</hi> but ſo, as that he was firſt aſſured by Count <hi>Maunſfelde</hi> (as by our intelligences &amp; letters intercepted it appéered) that the match for the towne was fully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before he would ſet out to it. Thither he came with his campe nowe of twelue thouſand footemen, and about foure thouſande horſe. He battered the Towne for ſhew, and vpon batterie, had it preſently yéelded without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault. The E. of <hi>Leyceſter</hi> hearing of the princes prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations towards <hi>Graue,</hi> being as yet vnreadie and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all meanes to furniſh a campe ſufficient to méete with him on equall ground in fielde, yet to the entent to be néere at hand with the forces he had, and to waite ſuch aduantages as occaſion might offer, with a ſmall campe of about thrée thouſand foote, and one thouſande horſe, he paſſed in perſon the riuer of <hi>Rhyne</hi> at <hi>Arnham</hi> in <hi>Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150835:6"/> into the prouince of <hi>Bettowe,</hi> with intent from thence to paſſe the riuer of <hi>Wale</hi> alſo, and ſo to approch to <hi>Graue</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bettowe</hi> is a prouince in <hi>Gelderland,</hi> lying betwéen the riuers of <hi>Rhyne</hi> and <hi>Wale,</hi> verie fertile, and then who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie helde by the enimie, or at leaſt infeſted by him, with his fortes of <hi>Luyteſforte,</hi> and <hi>Berckſhoofe</hi> and the two ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of <hi>Alon</hi> and <hi>Bemell.</hi> It was firſt thought expedient to win theſe fortes and caſtles before further paſſage: but they were verie ſtrong, well manned, and ſufficiently prouided of all neceſſaries. The great citie of <hi>Newmegen</hi> was but ouer the <hi>Wale</hi> on the other ſide very néere them, and the enimy with his campe at <hi>Graue,</hi> not eight engliſh miles from them. Theſe good helpes ſo néere, encouraged greatly the ſouldiours within, who with all warlike ſkill omitted nothing that mought be required in ſouldiours for defence. But the reſolution was to attempt them, which was done with ſuch valure of our ſouldiours, his Excellencie himſelfe ordering the batteries at ſome of them, and without reſpect of trauel or danger, putting his owne hand to the trenches, and other workes to be made for the approches, as at length at ſeuerall times they were all yéelded.</p>
            <p>Another thing of good importaunce was then to be done alſo. A little aboue the <hi>Towlehuiſe</hi> in <hi>Cleueland</hi> is a ſmall Iſlande in the riuer of <hi>Rhyne,</hi> in place where the <hi>Rhyne</hi> diuiding himſelfe, taketh the right hande courſe downe to <hi>Arnham,</hi> and retaineth ſtill the name of <hi>Rhyne,</hi> and on the left hand paſſeth to <hi>Newmegen,</hi> and is in Latin called <hi>Vahalis,</hi> in vulgar Dutch the <hi>Wale.</hi> The Iſlande is called <hi>Grauenſwert,</hi> and being fortified might commaunde both the riuers of <hi>Rhyne</hi> and <hi>Wale</hi> from that place down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that nothing coulde paſſe to <hi>Arnham</hi> or <hi>Newmegen.</hi> It was thought verie important to ſurpriſe this Iſlande, and to builde a forte in it: but the matter required celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:150835:6"/> ſecrecie, and good ſtrength of men, bicauſe the enimie was néere. It was committed to be done to ſir <hi>Martin Skenck,</hi> (he was now knighted before at <hi>Vtricht,</hi> and had giuen him by his Excellencie, at his receiuing of knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood a chaine of golde of a thouſand crownes) ſir <hi>Martin</hi> whiles his Excellencie was occupied in winning the forts and caſtles, tooke the Iſland, built the forte, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing left it defenſible and well manned, returned againe to his Excellencie: who hauing nowe gotten the fortes and caſtles, and ſo cléered the whole prouince of <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towe,</hi> and left not one enimie in it, thought fit to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede in his principall intent of drawing néere the enimie at <hi>Graue.</hi> He had firſt to paſſe the riuer of <hi>Wale,</hi> &amp; then to marche eight engliſh miles in the enimies countries, to the <hi>Maſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Graue,</hi> where the prince &amp; his campe lay. As he began to prouide his paſſage ouer the <hi>Wale</hi> the newes were ſodainly brought him that <hi>Graue</hi> was yéelded. This ſéemed ſo ſtrange that it was not at the firſt beléeued, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well bicauſe it was knowne to be of great ſtrength, and victualed, and thorowly prouided of all neceſſaries for nine Monethes, as alſo and more ſpecially for that his <hi>Excellencie</hi> had receiued two letters from Baron <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mart,</hi> captaine of <hi>Graue,</hi> the one the daie before, the other the ſame day: wherein <hi>Hemart</hi> wiſhed his Excellencie to do what elſe he thought conuenient, and to haue no care of <hi>Graue,</hi> for he was well able to defend it againſt all men, for one halfe yéere. Theſe letters were ſent to the <hi>Q. Maieſtie:</hi> but in the ende the newes were found true. The Town was yéelded; and his Excellencie bethinking him what was fit to be done, and ſéeing his army nothing equall to the enimies, the numbers being ſo far different, as is before rehearſed: vnderſtanding alſo that almoſt all the Townes néere about, as <hi>Bomell, Arnham, Amerſfort, Deuenter,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Guelders</hi> and <hi>Oueriſſell</hi> ſtoode in tickle tearmes likely to yéelde if the enimie came néere
<pb facs="tcp:150835:7"/> them: and finding indéede that the prince had alreadie ſent part of his armie towards <hi>Bomelſverte:</hi> he ſent foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſtrong garriſons into the next frontire Townes, and <hi>Bomell</hi> being thought to be then in ſome danger, himſelfe went thither, with fiftéene hundred footemen, and fiue hundred horſe, where he aſſured that Towne, and the Iſland being of great importaunce, and tooke ſuch order for the reſt as that time and the ſmall meanes he then had would permit. <hi>Hemart</hi> for his ſodaine yéelding of <hi>Graue</hi> without good cauſe, being ſufficiently furniſhed of all neceſſaries for defence and contrarie to aſſuraunce of it, giuen by his owne letters but the ſame day, and the day before, comming to <hi>Bomell</hi> was there apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and caried to <hi>Vtricht,</hi> his proces drawne, and in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne aſſemblie by Co. <hi>Hollock</hi> himſelfe and all the reſt of the Coronels and Martiall officers, of the Dutch, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, and diuers other nations adiudged to die, and was publikely executed accordingly, with two others of his captaines. I will not ſpeak of what difficultie the matter was thought to do this executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the party being a baron, of a Barons liuing, &amp; great by birth and alliance in thoſe parts: his Excellencie, a ſtranger: the Eſtate in broken termes: and the example there ſcant ſéene before. But the fact fell out ſo plaine, that his Excellencie woulde not be intreated but that iuſtice ſhoulde procéede: the iudges coulde not but condemne him, and the people though ſorye for the man yet much reioiced to ſée the iuſtice done. Amongeſt diuers others nowe ſent to ſtrengthen the garrions in ſundrye places, ſir <hi>Martin Skenck,</hi> and ſir <hi>Roger Williams</hi> were appointed with certaine horſe &amp; footmen, to ſée if they might enter <hi>Venloe,</hi> whither it was thought the enimie would make his next iourney. <hi>Venloe</hi> is a Towne of the Dutchie of <hi>Gelders,</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate vpon the riuer of <hi>Maſe,</hi> ſeauen or eight engliſh miles from <hi>Graue,</hi> &amp; then in the gouernment of ſir <hi>Martin
<pb facs="tcp:150835:7"/> Skenck,</hi> who had garriſon in it of ſeauen hundred dutch ſouldiours: but himſelfe was abſent, and attempting to get into it went as I ſaie with ſir <hi>Roger Williams,</hi> and about a hundred horſe, But they founde themſelues pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, and all the paſſages taken by the enimie. But yet minding to aſſay if with their horſemen they might poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie breake through the gardes, they gaue in the night a ſodaine moſt valiaunt attempt, vpon the whole campe, and ſlue manie euen néere to the princes owne lodging. But directing themſelues towardes the Towne, and finding the turnpikes ſhut, and garded with ſtrong watch of Muſkeyteires, and the campe nowe all vp in armes, and the day drawing on: they turned their courſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Wachtendoucke,</hi> a Towne of the Eſtates, ſeauen or eight miles of, where themſelues and manie of their companie entred, and ſaued themſelues from the whole cauallarie of the enimie, now purſuing them, ſome thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or fortie of their company were ſlaine, and taken. The prince then planted thorowly his ſiedge of <hi>Venloe,</hi> which the townes men in ſhort ſpace yéelded to him, whiles the ſouldiours ſtoode at defence of the walles. Whiles theſe things were thus in doing in thoſe partes the L. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughbie</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Berghes apzome</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> hauing intelligence of a great Conuoy of victuall, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouiſions to be brought out of the furder partes of <hi>Brabant,</hi> next <hi>Cleueland,</hi> and <hi>Lukeland,</hi> into <hi>Antwerpe:</hi> and hauing good aduertiſement of the time of their comming, vpon the <hi>23.</hi> of Maie, he met with them in their waie about eight or ten engliſh miles from <hi>Antwerpe:</hi> himſelf had with him thrée cornets of horſe, and three companies of foote: the conuoy was foure hundred wagons, and garded with ſouldiours, and of the countrie people, to the number of a thouſande. He ſet vpon them, ſlue, and put to flight all the people, burnt and ſpoiled almoſt all the wagons, and prouiſions, and ſome mares, wagons, and
<pb facs="tcp:150835:8"/> ſuch other things as he thought fit he brought away with him to <hi>Berghes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The E. of <hi>Leyceſter</hi> in the meane time hauing placed ſtrong garriſons in al his frontiers, began to imploy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wholie to the gathering of a ſufficient armie to méete with the prince in fielde: footemen in good numbers were gotten out of Englande, with ſome from Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: two thouſande Germaine horſes were appointed to be brought by Count <hi>Mewres,</hi> with a regiment of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine footemen, and a thouſand pyoners. But that the forces now readie mought be doing, whiles the others to make vp the full armie were in prouiding, his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſent into <hi>Flaunders,</hi> vnder the conduction of Count <hi>Mourice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and of his Nephew ſir <hi>Phillip Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> about two thouſand footemen, which with great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie and valure ſurpriſed the Towne of <hi>Axell,</hi> with foure ſtrong fortes néere about it, ſlue and put to flight foure bandes of footemen in the Towne, had rich ſpoyle, brought away fiue Enſignes of the enimies, left coronell <hi>Pyron,</hi> with eight or nine hundred ſouldiours in garriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and came their way, to the intent to attempt <hi>Graueling</hi> in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> which by a deceitfull traine laide for him by <hi>La Mote,</hi> was promiſed to ſir <hi>Phillip Sidney,</hi> who came thither, but finding the fraude, returned with the loſſe of about thirtie common ſouldiours. Thoſe of <hi>Axell</hi> had by this time cut the dikes, and by letting in the ſea, drowned the countrie to the wals of <hi>Axell,</hi> and <hi>Hulst,</hi> and thereby added great ſtrength to <hi>Axell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shortly after this, the Count <hi>Hollock,</hi> and ſir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Pellham,</hi> L. Marſhall of the fielde, made a roade into <hi>Brabant,</hi> where hauing waſted and ſpoiled <hi>Lange Strate,</hi> and a great part of the countrey, they returned without hearing of any enimie to reſiſt them.</p>
            <p>The prince after the yéelding of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enloe</hi> marched to <hi>Nuyſe,</hi> a Towne of the dioceſſe of <hi>Colloigne,</hi> helde for the
<pb facs="tcp:150835:8"/> elector <hi>Trucſes,</hi> by a valiant yoong gentleman, called <hi>Clowte.</hi> After ſome ſkirmiſhes, and a little batterie, and <hi>Clowte</hi> wounded, this Towne was loſt, by the coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of <hi>Clowtes</hi> ſoldiers, and <hi>Clowte</hi> taken out of his chamber wounded, and hanged out at the windowe with ſome note of vnſoldierlike vſage.</p>
            <p>From thence came the prince to <hi>Bercke,</hi> wherin were ſir <hi>Martin Skenck</hi> and coronell <hi>Morgan,</hi> with twelue hundred Engliſh, and ſeauen or eight hundred other ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours. This Towne is alſo of the dioceſſe of <hi>Colloigne,</hi> and held for the elector <hi>Trucſes.</hi> And though being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the limits of his Excellencies iuriſdiction, it may ſéem it appertained not to his charge, as in like ſorte <hi>Nuyſe</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: yet for the importaunce of the place to the vnited Prouinces ſtanding vpon the riuer of the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> and for the communitie, and néere coniunction and dependencie of both cauſes one on the other, <hi>vz.</hi> of the elector <hi>Truc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and of the Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces, it was thought expedient that the Towne ſhould be defended with common aide, and therefore ſuch garriſon before rehearſed was put into it. The Towne at the beginning when this garriſon came in about the time of the loſſe of <hi>Venlo</hi> was very weake, and through a contention for it betwéene the Prince elector <hi>Trucſes</hi> and <hi>Adolphe</hi> Count of <hi>Meurs,</hi> vnprouided almoſt of all neceſſaries. But his Excellencie hauing a little before quieted the ſtrife betwéene thoſe two, it was now ſomwhat ſupplied of prouiſions by the Eſtates, and repaired by the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie and trauell of Sir <hi>Martin</hi> and his ſoldiers. The ſiege began in the end of Iuly, and was continued on without great effect, partly through the valure of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and ſoldier within it, who made diuers ſalies, and often intercepted, and ſlew ſundrie of the enimies ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: but eſpecially by reaſon of the many continuall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements brought daily to the Princes campe of a
<pb facs="tcp:150835:9"/> great armie of his Excellencies now gathered and in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines to march. And indéed about this time had the Erle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> collected his forces, and prepared his prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and about the <hi>14.</hi> of Auguſt, ſent ſir <hi>Iohn Norris,</hi> &amp; ſir <hi>Thomas Cecill</hi> with the vantguard to paſſe the riuer <hi>Yſſell</hi> on his bridge of boates, at the foot of <hi>Yſſellort</hi> a mile aboue <hi>Arnham,</hi> with direction to encamp <hi>6.</hi> or <hi>7.</hi> miles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Cleueland,</hi> at a place called <hi>S. <hi>Seuenter</hi>
               </hi> vpon the banke of the <hi>Rhine.</hi> On the <hi>17.</hi> of Auguſt was ſent thither to him ſir <hi>William Pelham</hi> L. Marſhall of the armie with another troupe, and on the <hi>19.</hi> his Excellencie departed from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricht</hi> to <hi>Rhenen,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Arnham,</hi> where he ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till the troupes of <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> with Co. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Frizeland</hi> with Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> met him there. And when they were all come togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, on ſaturday the xxvij. of Auguſt he departed from <hi>Arnham,</hi> accompanied with the Prince of <hi>Portugall <hi>Don Emanuell,</hi>
               </hi> the Prince elector of <hi>Colloigne <hi>Trucſes,</hi>
               </hi> Co. <hi>Mourice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Co. <hi>Hollock,</hi> Co. <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Erle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> generall of the Engliſh horſemen, Count <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Count <hi>Solmes,</hi> Count <hi>Ouerſteyne,</hi> L. <hi>Willoughbie,</hi> L. <hi>North,</hi> S. <hi>Phillip Sidney,</hi> and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, noblemen, knights, and gentlemen, and with the reſt of the armie marched that night to <hi>Elten</hi> in <hi>Cleueland.</hi> At <hi>Elten</hi> his Excellencie thought expedient himſelfe to take view of his armie, which he did on ſunday the <hi>28.</hi> of Auguſt, and finding the bands of Engliſh and Iriſh not to fill the number of fiue thouſand footemen: the reſt of all nations not to make <hi>2000.</hi> the Cauallerie of all ſorts not to excéede the number of <hi>1400.</hi> knowing the enimie to be <hi>12000.</hi> ſtrong on foote, and <hi>3500.</hi> horſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced ſoldiers, he fell into conſultation what were fitteſt to be done. To reléeue <hi>Berck</hi> was the principall intent, or at leaſt to get the ſoldiers ſafe and honorably out of it. This was to be effected by one of two meanes.
<pb facs="tcp:150835:9"/> Either by aſſailing or diuerting the enimie. The firſt was full of difficulties. The enimie was ſtrong, he was in his place of ſtrength, he had his retraits at hand. Our campe was fewer in number, we ſhould come a long march into a ſtrange place, we had no retrait with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in twentie miles. And which tooke away all deliberation: our victuals vnſufficient, either for maintenance of the armie, or for reliefe of the towne, muſt néedes haue fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs. Diuerſion therefore was thought to be the way, and that to be done by the ſiege of ſome place that might force the enimie to ariſe to ſuccour it. And that place was reckoned fitteſt, to be <hi>Duiſbourge. Duiſbourge</hi> is a towne of the Countie of <hi>Zutphen,</hi> ſcituate at the confluence of the riuer called old <hi>Iſſell,</hi> with that péece of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> that ſeparating himſelfe from the bodie of the <hi>Rhine</hi> a little eaſt of <hi>Arnham,</hi> was anciently called <hi>Foſſa Druſiana,</hi> as a ditch cut and made by <hi>Druſius</hi> from the <hi>Rhine</hi> into <hi>Iſſell.</hi> The Towne was alſo called <hi>Druſii burgum.</hi> It was and is now the chamber of the Countie of <hi>Zutphen:</hi> well peopled and reaſonably rich, walled round with a high and ſtrong wall, and watered of good depth and breadth round, and in the greateſt part double: ſo that in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſoldiers it was thought of good ſtrength.</p>
            <p>This Towne beſides that being of importance, it was like to draw the enimie from <hi>Bercke</hi> to ſuccour it, it was perilous alſo for our armie to be left vngotten behind vs, for that lieng almoſt in the way of our paſſage betwéene <hi>Arnham</hi> and the campe, we muſt haue béene conſtrained, if we had procéeded to <hi>Bercke</hi> to haue left good forces for the aſſurance of that paſſage. There was in it captaine <hi>Sampſon,</hi> a valiant old ſoldier, a Wallon, with <hi>300,</hi> ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and about <hi>500.</hi> Burgers that bare armes. The reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution being taken for the ſiege of this Towne, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie not knowing but they ſhould paſſe on to <hi>Bercke:</hi> vpon the ſodaine his Excellencie appointed Count <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150835:10"/> with the Erle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> ſir <hi>Phillip Sidney</hi> and others, with ſeauen or <hi>800.</hi> foote, and <hi>500.</hi> horſe to march by night, and taking the paſſages of the towne to begin the ſiege by the breake of the day on tweſday the <hi>30.</hi> of Auguſt. His Excellencie with the whole armie that day followed marching back thither from <hi>Elten</hi> in an order woorth the noting, for that the bands extended to the vttermoſt made ſhow of fourtéen or fiftéene thouſand, whereas indéed horſe and foote both were not complete eight thouſande. He came earely that afternoone to <hi>Duiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourge:</hi> and himſelfe in perſon within arcabuze ſhot tooke viewe of the wals, on al the eaſt ſide, and that night ſet pyoners and ſoldiers to intrenching within halfe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabuze ſhot. Our ordinance was not yet come. The next night his Excellencie vnderſtanding that our pyoners had left their worke at the trenches: himſelfe betwéene eleuen and twelue of the clocke at night, went with ſir <hi>William Pelham</hi> and ſome few of his garde to ſée what was doing, and being within thréeſcore yeardes of the Towne ditch, both going togither, a muſket ſhot from the wall ſtroke ſir <hi>William Pelham</hi> moſt dangerouſly in the bellie, but pierced not his entrailes, ſo that he eſcaped death, and was abroade againe within two daies. The next day came our ordinance, and the morning after it was planted. Then had we alſo newes that the prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> being certified of our ſitting downe here, woulde be with vs within foure daies. Wherewith the former opinion of his Excellencie for the leuie of the princes campe by this diuerſion was fully confirmed. The orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance being ten péeces plaied on Friday the ſecond of September, from the breake of day till two in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, his Excellencie being continually hard by them in the trenches, and had made two breaches reaſonablie aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultable, but yet ſo filled vp againe by thoſe within, with logs, earth, bedding, and ſuch other traſh, that the aſſault
<pb facs="tcp:150835:10"/> was difficult, eſpecially a water of a yard and more déepe and thréeſcore foote broade being betwéene the aſſailors and the wall. But ſuch was the courage of our men of all nations, that without further batterie they extorted with great importunitie from his Excellencie being in the trenches, a reſolution for a preſent aſſault. And the contention being great betwéene the leaders to whom the honour of the aſſault ſhoulde be giuen, it was orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Excellencie that Count <hi>Hollocke</hi> with the Dutch and Scots: ſir <hi>Iohn Norris</hi> with the Engliſh and Iriſh, ſhould ech attempt one breach. They foorthwith or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered their ſquadrons accordingly, with ſo generall courage and ioy, as was maruellous to behold, and did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede daunt the enimie more (as themſelues afterwardes confeſſed) than any thing elſe that was done. Great alſo and many and moſt earneſt were the particular ſuites of priuate noble men, and gentlemen, for leaue to go to the aſſault: which his Excellencie would grant to verie few of them. The ſquadrons ſtanding at the water ſide rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to paſſe to the aſſault, the enimies within hauing hitherto valiantly and ſoldierlike carried themſelues, and now laboring to repaire the breaches, and ſtanding in armes to receiue vs, yet ſéeing preſently before their eies their owne imminent danger, &amp; eſpecially mooued with the reſolution of our people, they offered firſt an accord vpon conditions, which his Excellencie refuſed, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they yéelded ſimplie, with grant of life to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſoldier onely. Which being accepted the towne was rendred, and ſir <hi>Iohn Boroughes</hi> and ſir <hi>William Stanley</hi> appointed to the garde of it, till further order. This Exploite being happily atchiued without loſſe, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aduiſe it was reſolued to ſtay there a while, aſwell to take order for the ſafe kéeping of the towne, as alſo to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide there the princes comming with his campe, if he had meaning to ſéeke vs: and eſpecially for that neither
<pb facs="tcp:150835:11"/> victuals nor furniture for our ordinance were then come ſufficient for any further preſent attempt. There were two or thrée engliſh miles from <hi>Duiſborough</hi> ſomwhat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Zutphen,</hi> a caſtle called <hi>Voerdon,</hi> &amp; a ſtrong place cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hackfourd</hi> houſe, held by the enimy, which greatly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noied thoſe parts. It was thought expedient in the meane time to take in theſe caſtle &amp; houſe, for which cauſe certain companies were ſent thither. They anſwered at the firſt ſtoutly. But afterwards being made beléeue the cannon was at hand they yéelded. Our newes came often to <hi>Duiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroughe,</hi> that the prince with his campe was riſen from <hi>Berck:</hi> That he had laide his bridge ouer the <hi>Rhyne</hi> with intent to paſſe towardes vs: and indéede he was whyles we lay there, paſſed with his armie, and, as we learned, minded to haue aſſaied the ſuccouring of <hi>Duiſbourge,</hi> if it had not béene taken ſooner then he expected. But hearing it was gone, and vnderſtanding that our campe laie (as indéed it did) verie ſtrongly, he ſtaied on this ſide the <hi>Rhyne</hi> néere <hi>Weeſell,</hi> about thirtie engliſh miles from vs, with intent to returne, and to procéed in the ſiege of <hi>Berck</hi> as we were verie credibly enformed. The E. of <hi>Leyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> hauing now ſet full order in the towne, his prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being come, and finding that the prince made no haſte towards him in that place, though he might haue ſéemed to haue attained his principall intent, in raiſing the ſiege of <hi>Berck,</hi> with ſome ouerplus of aduantage in getting <hi>Duiſbourge,</hi> yet to drawe the prince further away from <hi>Berck</hi> that it might be wholie reléeued, as alſo for diuers other good reaſons, he reſolued to depart thence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Zutphen,</hi> and accordingly on the thirtéene of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, marched thither with his whole campe, and there ſat downe, about an engliſh mile from the towne, on the riuer ſide next <hi>Zutphen,</hi> and the princes campe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zutphen</hi> is the chiefe towne of the Countie of <hi>Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> ſcituate on the eaſt banke of the riuer <hi>Yſſell,</hi> about
<pb facs="tcp:150835:11"/> equall diſtance of ſixe or ſeauen engliſh miles from <hi>Duiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourge</hi> on the ſouth, and from <hi>Deuenter</hi> on the northeaſt quarter. It is of it ſelfe ſtrong: but important in this only, that it hindreth the frée paſſage of the <hi>Yſſell</hi> in the places néere about it. But on the north weſt ſide of the riuer right ouer againſt <hi>Zutphen,</hi> and within muſket ſhot of the Towne in the prouince of the <hi>Vellowe,</hi> in the Duchie of <hi>Gelders,</hi> were two forts, called the forts of <hi>Zutphen,</hi> ſuch of importance, as they ſpoiled the whole prouince of the <hi>Vellowe,</hi> and made the countrie yéeld them large contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions euen from the ports of <hi>Vtricht, Amsterdam,</hi> and <hi>Leiden</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> being <hi>50.</hi> miles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. For ſtrength they were accounted impregnable, and might be ſupplied from the Towne by great paſſagde boates with al neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. The Eſtates campe two yéeres before had lieu at them ten moneths, with eleuen thouſand footemen, and <hi>3000.</hi> horſe, and departed with loſſe without them. <hi>Taxis</hi> a ſoldier of account with the enimie, lieutenant to Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Verdugo</hi> gouernour of <hi>Frizeland</hi> for the king of Spaine, commanded in the towne and forts. After aduiſe taken, vpon good view of the place, it was reſolued, that the forts as of more importance for vs, and not the town, ſhould be beſieged. Our bridge of boates was appointed to be laid ouer the riuer about an Engliſh mile from the Towne, and the campe to be placed on both ſides the water: that the prince if he came and thought fit, mought ſée that we would giue him the opportunitie to attempt vs. Order being taken for theſe things, whiles they were in doing: his Excellencie vnderſtanding the tickle eſtate of <hi>Deuenter,</hi> thought fit himſelfe in perſon to go thither, leauing ſtraight charge to be ſpéedily aduertiſed, if at the campe they ſhould vnderſtand any thing of the Princes moouing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deuenter</hi> is the chiefe citie of the prouince of <hi>Oueriſſell.</hi> One of the <hi>Haunſe</hi> townes, large, ſtrong, rich, and direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:150835:12"/> indéede <hi>Swowle</hi> and <hi>Campen,</hi> and the reſt of the cities and townes of that countrie, which in a manner depende wholy vpon it. It is ſeated vpon the northeaſt bank of the riuer <hi>Yſſell.</hi> It then ſtoode in a kinde of newtrall termes inclining more in ſhew to the Eſtates party, but yéelding no contributions to the war, and indéed aiding the enimie with victuals and prouiſions, and ſome of the towne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſecret and ſtrict intelligences with him. That was the cauſe of his Excellencies ſo ſpéedie repaire thither: the caſe being taken to be ſuch, as that who had come firſt of the prince or him with forces, ſhould haue béene receiued. And indéede the prince as we after vnderſtood, haſtened al he could thither. But his Excellencie was firſt entred, and with him about foure hundred footemen, and two or thrée cornets of horſe, and no moe at this time. He dealt in courteous and gentle ſort with the towneſmen, and they likewiſe vſed him and his well: but yet ſo, as they woulde not lodge as in garriſon anie of thoſe he brought with him. He had not béene there full two daies when certaine aduertiſement came to him from the camp, that the prince with his whole armie was riſen from about <hi>Weeſell,</hi> and come to <hi>Burckloe,</hi> a towne of the territorie of <hi>Munster,</hi> about eight engliſh miles from our campe. Wherevpon his Excellencie departed preſently with his owne traine to the campe, leauing the foure hundred footemen, and two cornets of horſe in <hi>Deuenter,</hi> and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the camp the trenches vpon <hi>Zutphen</hi> ſide not fully finiſhed, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded all diligence to be vſed therin, ſo as in one day they were ſufficiently made vp, &amp; wel furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſoldiers, and al neceſſaries ready for defence. The next night the prince came to <hi>Zutphen,</hi> with <hi>1500.</hi> horſe, and the morning after departed, leauing part of his horſe men there, and returned to his campe at <hi>Burckloe,</hi> where whiles he ſtaied prouiding victuals as we vnderſtoode for <hi>Zutphen,</hi> and the forts, our men ſpent the time in intren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:150835:12"/> and fortifieng about the two forts, where, as alſo vpon the towne ſide happened diuers light ſkirmiſhes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt euery day, till vpon the <hi>21.</hi> of September in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Excellencie hauing intelligence that the Prince would the next morning ſend a conuoy of victuals into <hi>Zutphen,</hi> ſent out good ſcowt that night, and gaue order to ſir <hi>Iohn Norris</hi> to drawe out ſir <hi>William Stanleies,</hi> and ſome other bands of footemen, and appointed ſome horſemen withall to encounter the conuoy in the way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the enimies campe, and <hi>Zutphen.</hi> In the morning the <hi>22.</hi> of September fell a great and thicke miſt, that you might hardly diſcerne a man ten paces of, at the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp whereof the enimies appéered ſo néere our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, hauing planted all their muſkets and arcabuzes being <hi>2000.</hi> and their pikes being a thouſande, very ſtrongly on the high way, as our men, ſpecially the noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and gentlemen, as the Erle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughbie,</hi> ſir <hi>Phillip Sidney,</hi> ſir <hi>William Ruſſell,</hi> ſir <hi>Iohn Norris,</hi> and the reſt, in number ſeuen or eight ſcore, who were in troupe togither in the face of the enimie before our footemen, receiued the whole volie of the enimies ſhot, and paſſing the very furie of it, gaue charge vpon the two formoſt troupes of the enimies horſemen, and draue them backe ouer their owne trenches, and within their pikes at two ſeuerall times, in ſuch ſort, as Count <hi>Hanniball Gonzaga</hi> a man for nobilitie and ſeruice of ſpeciall account amongſt them, was there ſlaine, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others with him. Captaine <hi>George Creſier</hi> an Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe of ſingular valure and ſkill, was taken priſoner, and two of their cornets brought away. We loſt about thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, one and other, ſlaine, and dying after of hurts, but not any of name, ſaue onely ſir <hi>Phillip Sidney,</hi> who firſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one horſe ſhot vnder him, and mounted vpon a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond was ſhot with a muſket in the left thigh, but came home on his horſe, and died the <hi>25.</hi> day after. His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie
<pb facs="tcp:150835:13"/> hauing béene in the field giuing order from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and now receiuing the newes of this good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, was ſomewhat of opinion to haue brought downe the whole campe, and to haue ſet vpon the enimie with all our forces. But vpon better conſideration by aduiſe of all the chiefe officers of the field, we being not paſt <hi>300.</hi> horſe, &amp; <hi>16.</hi> or <hi>17.</hi> hundred footmen, that might preſently come to fight, the reſt being imploied at the forts, and in other neceſſarie ſeruices at that time: the enimie being thrée thouſand footemen ſtrong in place, and <hi>12.</hi> or <hi>14.</hi> hundred horſe, and we doubting leaſt his whole armie had béene there, which it might well haue béene, being the night before but fiue miles of, it was reſolued that our troupes ſhould ſtay, and not to commit the whole to the fortune of that day. So this hot ſkirmiſh ended, our men content with their victorie returning, and the enimie marching quietly away.</p>
            <p>After this fight we heard no more of the Prince in <hi>10.</hi> or <hi>12.</hi> daies. But our certaine intelligences gaue vs, that he was gone to méete with our Reyters and Almaines, (now thought to be readie to march,) with intent to ſtay them either by ſtopping their paſſage, or by fight, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as alſo to prouide more victuals, powder, and ſhot for <hi>Zutphen.</hi> His Excellencie ſtill applied his principall purpoſe in beſieging the forts. There is a péece of ground on the ſide of the riuer that <hi>Zutphen</hi> is, and within ſixtie yards of the towne, called the Iſland, but it is drie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the towne. The taking of it was accounted of great importance for the winning of the forts, but full of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, lying ſo néere the towne, and the enimie hauing a ſconce in it fortified and manned with thirtie men. His Excellencie was ſundrie times promiſed the ſurpriſing of this Iſland by ſome, but performance not following, one night himſelfe imparting his purpoſe to two cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines onely, went out at ten of clocke in the night, (the
<pb facs="tcp:150835:13"/> prince elector <hi>Trucſes,</hi> the Erle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and the L. <hi>North</hi> being with him) and gaue order for a preſent ſurpriſe of it, which ſo happily ſuccéeded, that the place and ſconſe were ſuddenly taken, the men within, two or thrée taken priſoners, ſome ſlaine, the reſt fled, or were drowned in the water, and not a man of ours loſt or hurt. Now to kéepe this place was great danger, and ſome would néeds perſwade to haue it left. His Excellencie would not ſo, but fell foorthwith in hand to intrenching, and hauing made it defenſible, he then abandoned the former ſeate of campe, and brought the bridge downe to this Iſland, and the whole campe néerer the forts, now indéede ſeriouſly attending by all militarie arts and deuices to win them. The hope of all our leaders both Engliſh and others, was ſmall for the obteining of theſe fortes: They were ſo ſtrong and well prouided euerie way, and our meanes ſcant ſufficient for ſo great an exploit. But his Excellencies owne ſelfe contrary to all and euery their aduiſes perſiſted in his intent moſt conſtantly, and would not heare anie thing that might tend to diſſwade him from this purpoſe: and as indéede about a worke of his owne, and of the commendation whereof very little can be deriued to any others, he moſt diligently and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly attended alwaies in perſon both earelie and late, and put his owne hand almoſt to euery particular ſeruice of it, ſconces were built, trenches were drawne, ſkirmiſhes made on both ſides, and nothing for offence, or defence omitted on either ſide, that militarie ſkill in like caſe coulde execute or inuent, till on the fourth of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the prince hauing béene aduertiſed by <hi>Taxis</hi> that the Iſlande was taken, and that our workes began to grow perillous to the fortes, came in perſon to <hi>Zutphen</hi> with his whole campe, with intent as we could gather, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt our trenches in the Iſlande on the towne ſide. He came the fourth of October at night, and on the morrow
<pb facs="tcp:150835:14"/> after, we certainely expected he ſhoulde haue aſſailed the Iſland, for the which he had great opportunities: himſelf with his campe being to come in the face on the eaſt and ſouth ſide, in a faire plaine capable of his armie vnder the town wal: the towne on the northeaſt beating on it with their great and ſmall ſhot, &amp; hauing a gate for ſalie within arcabuze ſhot: the <hi>Mill</hi> forte betwéene the towne and the water, hauing his artillarie bent on it: the great fort with his ordenance ready to plaie on the north ſide, and the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle forte ſomewhat néerer with muſket and arcabuze northeaſt, ſo that ſauing on the weſt and ſouth ſide they had compaſſed it round. But his Excellencie on the Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day at night, all night long had planted his ordenance to beate vpon the princes campe if it came: and hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed the trenches with ſtore of men, was ſufficently prouided for him. On the Wedneſday morning the fift of October, we ſawe of the princes troupes of horſe and foote raunge vp &amp; downe, a mile of and more. But hauing left ſome victuals and ſtore of men in the town, and doubting nothing of the loſſe of the ſconces, he departed that night two engliſh miles back, which aſſoone as his Excellencie vnderſtoode, the ſame Wedneſday at night he planted his ordinance both in the Iſland, &amp; on the other ſide the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt the little fort. On the Thurſday morning he battered the little but ſtrongeſt fort on both ſides, till two of the clock in the afternoone, &amp; then tooke it by aſſault ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in it <hi>300.</hi> ſoldiers in the face of the great fort with eight hundred ſoldiers, and of the towne where <hi>Taxis</hi> then was with aboue <hi>2000.</hi> and in hearing at leaſt of the prince, and his whole campe, hauing béene at <hi>Zutphen</hi> the daie before, and now not thrée engliſh miles of it. His Excellencie was all the time of this batterie and aſſault in the trenches in the Iſland on the towne ſide, and at the aſſault time with his pike in hande, verilie expecting a ſalie from the towne in that part, but none came. In this
<pb facs="tcp:150835:14"/> aſſault did M. <hi>Edward Stanley</hi> lieutenant to coronell ſir <hi>W. Stanley,</hi> &amp; captaine of one of his bands, being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the firſt for the aſſault, behaue himſelfe moſt valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; was with his valor the principall cauſe of this daies happy ſucceſſe, whom his Excellencie beholding made him therefore preſently knight in the trenches, gaue him fortie pounds ſterling in golde, and ſent him the next daie a patent of one hundred marks ſterling by yéer, during the life of the ſaide ſir <hi>Edward,</hi> binding his Excellencies own landes in England for the due paiment thereof, with a moſt honorable report of this his fact conteined in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. We loſt about eight men in this aſſault and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. His Excellencie appointed the next day for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching the great forte. But that night did all the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and ſoldiers within abandon it, leauing behinde them their ordenance, and eſcaped ouer the water to the towne where <hi>Taxis</hi> was faine to receiue them. There were taken from the enimie by our men during this ſiege two fortes mo, which the enimy had lately erected about thoſe others, and a caſtle called <hi>Niembeck</hi> caſtle his Excellencie himſelf in perſon tooke in, foure engliſh miles in the <hi>Vellow</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this place: beſides the caſtle of <hi>Boxbergen</hi> néere <hi>Deuenter,</hi> which we tooke alſo a little before this time. Great ioies were made in all the vnited Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the recouerie of theſe fortes. The whole countrie of the <hi>Vellow</hi> about fortie engliſh miles in breadth, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much in length, being thereby fully cléered: and no leſſe was the enimie daunted, hauing now loſt his whole foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in that countrie: and <hi>Taxis</hi> the gouernor hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him a goodly reuenew, which the contributions of that ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite vp to <hi>Amſtredam</hi> and <hi>Loyden</hi> did yéeld him. Vpon the departure of the prince from <hi>Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> his Excellencie diſpatched ſecretly ſir <hi>William Ruſſell</hi> and ſir <hi>Roger Williams,</hi> with fiue hundred horſe to attend vpon him, and to obſerue his march, who found
<pb facs="tcp:150835:15"/> him on the Friday at night the next day after the aſſault was giuen, about <hi>Burckloe,</hi> eight or ten engliſh miles from our campe, where they gaue alarme to his whole campe, beate in his ſcowtes and corps de gards, but not a man came foorth to them. The next day the prince mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vp towards <hi>Ringlebert,</hi> a houſe of the duke of <hi>Cleues,</hi> about thrée or foure engliſh miles from <hi>Weeſell,</hi> where he lay craſed as we harde of an ague, and diſperſed his campe about in the villages adioining, ſince which time till his returne to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> we harde nothing of him. His Excellencie after he had ſo honorably, and with ſo ſmall loſſe in ſo ſhort time, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe forts, thought before very hard to be won: hauing deliuered <hi>Berck</hi> alſo, which was the principall intent of his firſt marching, and ſir <hi>Martin Skenck</hi> with diuers of our engliſh, being come from thence to his campe at <hi>Zutphen</hi> to him: ſéeing his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines and Reyters came not: and finding the enimie quietly gone, hauing nothing elſe to do in fielde, and the time of yéere far ſpent, being about the midſt of October, determined by aduiſe of his counſaile, to giue order for guarde and defence of the fortes, and to withdrawe his ſoldiers from the Iſlande, and other places, and ſo to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe his army. Which things the better to effect, himſelf with the chiefe of his counſaile went to <hi>Deuenter:</hi> min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding withal to aſſay the garriſoning of that place, being a matter of great importance. But being called away from thence to <hi>Arnham,</hi> where ſir <hi>Philip Sidney</hi> then laie in great danger: &amp; by the death of ſir <hi>Phillip</hi> retiring himſelf with extreame griefe and ſorrow to <hi>Vtricht:</hi> he gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before his departure for the garriſoning of <hi>Deuenter,</hi> and changing of the magiſtrate there to the prince elector of <hi>Colloigne <hi>Trucſes,</hi>
               </hi> ſir <hi>William Pelham,</hi> and ſir <hi>Iohn Norris,</hi> who with ſome little ſtur and danger, effected both accordingly, and left gouernor of the garriſon there ſir <hi>William Stanley,</hi> with <hi>1200</hi> footemen Engliſh and
<pb facs="tcp:150835:15"/> Iriſh, and two hundred horſe.</p>
            <p>Whiles this was in doing at <hi>Deuenter,</hi> there fell out a great and gallant ſkirmiſh at the campe in this ſort. Order being giuen for diſmiſſing the troupes into garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, firſt ſome companies, then others were ſent awaie, and now it was thought expedient to abandon the tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches on the other ſide of the water next <hi>Zutphen:</hi> and ſo to take vp the bridge and come away. Firſt the larger trenches were left, and the men drawne into a ſmall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification at the bridge end, with intent the next night to take vp our bridge alſo. Which <hi>Taxis</hi> perceiuing from the towne, and ſéeing the ſmall companies remaining on that ſide, he ſalied with about two thouſand footemen, paſſed the firſt trenches forſaken, and aſſaulted the ſmall fortification remaining with great valure, himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the firſt in perſon. Our men being taken on the ſudden were at the firſt fiue or ſixe of them ſlaine: but the reſt ſtood manfully to it, at the pikes end, vntill ſir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Stanley</hi> comming ouer the bridge from the <hi>Vellowe</hi> ſide with ſupply of fiue or ſixe hundred footemen, and lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant <hi>Nicholas Parker</hi> with onely fiue horſemen, draue them away euen into the towne gate, and ſlew many of them, and were likely to haue entred the towne pell mel with them, if the ſoldiers had not béene ſtaied by their leaders. The next night we left this little fortification alſo, and tooke vp our bridge, and day by day, as it might conueniently be done, diſmiſſed the whole forces into garriſons.</p>
            <p>It may be demanded his Excellencie being now in a good courſe of proſperous procéeding: the Prince with his campe being gone, the forts taken, and nothing remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in thoſe quarters but the bare town of <hi>Zutphen:</hi> why the winning of that was not attempted alſo? To which this may be anſwered: The towne is of it ſelfe of ſmall importance without the forts, onely prohibiting the frée
<pb facs="tcp:150835:16"/> paſſage of the riuer by it: Then is it very ſtrong, well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of all neceſſaries, and at that time manned with two or thrée thouſand bearing armes: and the Prince though departed further of, yet houering with his armie not aboue twentie Engliſh miles of it, ſo that the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of it could not be but dangerous, the commoditie ſmall. But beſides, it remaineth ſo inuironed with our garriſons round about it, as it may be well ſaid to be now beſieged. In <hi>Deuenter</hi> ſixe Engliſh miles at northeſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the riuer ſide is ſir <hi>William Stanley</hi> with twelue hundred footemen, and two hundred horſe. In the forts of <hi>Zutphen</hi> on the <hi>Vellowe</hi> ſide within muſket ſhot of the towne at weſt, is maiſter <hi>Rowland Yorke</hi> with eight hundred footmen, and one hundred horſe. At <hi>Duiſbourge</hi> ſouthward ſixe miles, (and at <hi>Brunkhurst</hi> caſtell ſomwhat néerer) vpon the banke of <hi>Iſſell</hi> alſo is ſir <hi>Iohn Boroughes</hi> with eight hundred footmen, and two hundred horſe. The eaſt and ſoutheaſt quarters are ſhut vp with our garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of <hi>Lockham, Sherenberg, Doetecom:</hi> So that they of the garriſon of <hi>Zutphen</hi> can not ſtir out, neither can ſo much as victuals be brought to them, but by land: and that from twentie or thirtie miles of at leaſt: and through the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of our garriſons, which will require more forces than the Prince can often ſpare them, and more charges than the value of the towne will counteruaile. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our comming away, as ſoone as our campe was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, we heare that <hi>Taxis</hi> hath leſſened his garriſon to the number of two hundred, and put the Burgers out of the towne, meaning to ſpare victuals, which he hath in ſmall ſtore. For neither did the Prince bring him in much at the times he came thither, neither could or can he ſupply him at one time with any plentie for want of carriages. Beſides theſe, other cauſes alſo letted this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt <hi>Zutphen.</hi> The time of yéere was ſpent, the wants in our armie were very great, and our Reiters
<pb facs="tcp:150835:16"/> came not, who if they had not diſappointed vs, all impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments notwithſtanding his Excellencie had procéeded furder. And laſt of all it was thought we had done well for this yéere: more being indéed moſt happily atchieued, than was hoped for or purpoſed at our comming foorth. For the onely intent at the firſt ſetting out of this laſt campe was to raiſe the ſiege of <hi>Berke:</hi> yea, or if we could haue honourably deliuered our men that were in it, though the towne were loſt, it was thought a ſufficient péece of ſeruice, with ſo ſmall means againſt an enimie ſo puiſſant, &amp; with continuall late victories ſo greatly eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and feared. But God be thanked, who is the giuer of victories, and whoſe power for his poore afflicted appéered not obſcurely in theſe actions: <hi>Berke</hi> is cléerely deliuered, the Engliſh are all come from it: it is left well manned and otherwiſe prouided. And if we will ſummarily note all Gods bleſſings in theſe militarie ſeruices onely ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the miniſterie of his Excellencie during the time of his gouernement and abode there, it will appéere that in thoſe few monethes there haue béene taken by our men from the enimie aboue twentie townes, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, forts, and ſconces: that his footemen and his beſt footemen the Spanyards haue béen met withall at <hi>Graue,</hi> that his horſemen and his beſt horſemen the Albaneſes, and Italians, haue béene well encountred in the ſkirmiſh beſides <hi>Zutphen:</hi> that his ſtrong <hi>Zutphen</hi> forts were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by aſſault, euen in the ſight almoſt of himſelfe, and of his whole campe: that his armie ſo much redoubted and feared, was drawne from <hi>Berck</hi> to <hi>Zutphen:</hi> there abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, there encountred ſundry times, and at length retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe againe &amp; diſmiſſed without ſauing his forts, or doing vs any dammage, ſauing the loſſe of ſir <hi>Phillip Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> True it is, he hath gotten in this time <hi>Graue, Venloe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nuyſe:</hi> But <hi>Graue</hi> by ſuch means, as baron <hi>Hemart</hi> the gouernor by publique iudgement of his owne beſt friend
<pb facs="tcp:150835:17"/> and commander the Count <hi>Hollock,</hi> and of al other mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie officers of all nations, loſt his head for it. <hi>Venloe</hi> was yéelded by the towneſmen whiles the ſoldiers defended the wals. <hi>Nuyſe</hi> was not of the iuriſdiction, or territory of the vnited Prouinces, &amp; therefore his Excellencie had not to do with it. But this is true alſo, that in all theſe wars and ſundrie diuerſities of accidents and attempts in diuers places, the enimie neuer got one towne, caſtle, forte, or ſconce, wherein any one engliſh ſoldier was, nor did anie one péece of ſeruice woorth the noting ſince his Excellencie came into the fielde with this laſt armie. And let the Eſtates eſpecially, and the people of the vnited Prouinces acknowledge the goodnes of God in theſe his workes, and the great grace and fauor of her Maieſtie, in ſpending and ſending to and for them, her money, forces, and moſt valiant, noble, louing and beloued ſubiects, by whoſe ſeruice it is nowe done for them, that whereas their eſtate was at his Excellencies firſt arriuall, ſo vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly without hope of ſtanding as is ſhewed at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my letter: Nowe they are left in good aſſurance of ſafetie, religion by a ſynode being fully eſtabliſhed: the ciuill gouernment orderly ſetled: the militarie diſcipline well reſtored: their people in good obedience: their fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers in great hope of maintenance to be continued: their territorie in <hi>Gelders, Zutphen, Oueriſſell,</hi> and <hi>Flaunders</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged: their reuenew by a great acceſſion of contribution in <hi>Gelders</hi> and <hi>Oueriſſell</hi> increaſed: their doubtfull friends of <hi>Oueriſſell</hi> aſſured, and their enimie put to that plunge, as he yet hath not béene ſince his being in thoſe countries. God make them as thankfull to God and hir Maieſtie for it as they haue good cauſe: and to acknowledge it to his Excellencie as his franke and moſt behoouefull great ſeruice for them hath deſerued: whom if extremities of ſundrie kinde of great croſſes: plaine deſtitution and want almoſt of all fit meanes: priuate care of his owne
<pb facs="tcp:150835:17"/> moſt large expences for the publike: or often dangerous hazard of his perſon could haue withdrawne from this procéeding, nothing had béene done at this time. But God whom he ſerueth hath wrought this great worke out of all thoſe difficulties by him, to him be the praiſe and glory for it. His Excellencie after his campe thus diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and a little time ſpent at <hi>Vtricht</hi> in the publique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, departed thence to the <hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Hollande:</hi> where hauing eſtabliſhed perfect order in the ciuill and military gouernments during his abſence, being vpon important cauſes to returne into England, from <hi>Hage</hi> he paſſed by <hi>Delph, Rotterdam, Dort, Briell,</hi> and <hi>Vluſhing,</hi> where he embarked for England on the <hi>23.</hi> of Nouember at night, and on the next night was with her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> at Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monde, of whom he was moſt graciouſly receiued.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I béen bold to trouble you with this briefe diſcourſe, wherein if any thing ſet downe or omitted be not to your contentation, I hope you will conſider it hath procéeded by your owne earneſt vrging from him, who deſireth nothing more then to content you, and who but to pleaſe you had rather haue ſhewed his dutifull affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſome other matter. But thus much if it like you ſo well to interprete of it, may be as it were to giue you a taſte in theſe matters, till ſome of better ſkill and more leiſure may fully ſatiſfie it with a iuſt volume, which I wiſh indéed to be done, the argument will well beare it. And ſo remaining to do you what further ſeruice my ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der abilitie may aforde I ende.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At London <date>the <hi>8.</hi> of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie <hi>1586.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips humble <hi>in all ſeruice,</hi> T. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
